[Music]
we've been interested for quite a while
in the IDW Jordan Pederson and what
feels like a kind of great intellectual
awakening so far it's been a bit of a
countercultural phenomenon and a lot of
people are kind of described it as being
on the right or being against the left
and so what we're really interested in
doing is kind of unpicking what the left
has to learn from the IDW movement
itself whether you kind of agree with
them politically or whatever if you
watch some of these some of these
programs are there at Weinstein Bret
Weinstein Jordan Peterson Ben Shapiro
you realize that they are talking about
very fundamental things very important
fundamental things there's a real
awareness of the challenges that we face
as a society so it seems the right thing
to do is to try and understand that to
be part of that conversation and I'll
just say a part of what drew me into
listening more and more to these folks
is like being challenged and then saying
wow but they're also really smart
they're doing their conversations as you
said slowing conversations down instead
of five minutes sound bytes on legacy
media you know media forms which are so
simplifying and reductionistic it's
allowing people to sit and think out
loud together in long-form ways and
tease apart really complex ideas but
they're also able to touch on really
hot-button issues that have kind of been
off limits in certain ways especially
when you set them at the left the left
have certain topics and issues and if
you don't tow the line you can easily be
exiled or if nothing else questioned and
frowned upon but they're starting to
touch on some of these and you can say
what you want about many of them and
obviously I don't agree with a lot of
things a lot of them say but they're
modeling how to have conversations and
talk about things and they're smart
people and even if you disagree it's
really refreshing to have real discourse
and intellectual people talking about
really important issues and I will say I
mean I think you're right and you've
said this before around compared with
the right and the complete control over
the government the United States and
jail cells and guns and elite police and
military the left has more soft power
it's more in the academia and
universities also Hollywood and cultural
you know forms I will say when I was
first encountering Peterson and Ike
challenged but then intrigued by some of
his critiques to the left and then I
came talked about this that slide into
you know Soviet Union and and and
genocide and you know gulag but then I
was also hearing about Brett Weinstein
at Evergreen and I was really curious so
when I finally watched that live raw
footage of what happened to Evergreen it
was really shocking and it was like I
just didn't expect to see that you know
young people people of color and white
allies fighting for racial justice and
diversity inequity doing this mob
mentality of a white man who was a white
man but who's also a Bernie supporter
and Occupy Wall Street guy solidly on
the Left solidly and Ally and to watch
just how that unfolded and it ends by
them wandering the the campus with
baseball bats and disarming the police
and of course the president of the
college did not help with that situation
it brought up that question of like it's
not a gonna be this totalitarian
takeover but it's also not completely
benign if if you if you imagine people
gaining more power with that kind of
fanatic chaotic mob mentality which you
know people are implications critique
which I still grapple with is I think he
quotes Orson Welles or someone saying
the bourgeoisie it's not so they're not
driven so much by love for the poor as
much as by hatred and envy of the rich
and that's really touchy and that's a
fine line but I hear naming that when
sometimes when I see it playing out
folks on the Left I'm like doesn't feel
this open-hearted compassionate focus on
the poor it side there's a lot of shadow
a shadow and there's a need for direct
action and
to vism that disrupt systems but a point
that Bret Weinstein makes is that
universities are not the right target to
be channeling all that energy channel
that into organizing to vote out you
know Republicans in Congress or channel
that into you know protesting police
brutality and police violence like the
university is is this really safe
protected area that does already value
these things yeah and is so much more
progressive than society at large why
are you wasting energy well that's the
paradox I think because it's a soft
target right you can have wins yeah like
if you if you target your kind of
accusations of bigotry at progressive
people they will take it seriously
oh my god and I'm sorry am I am I is
there a microaggression here I'm and
where is the people on the right yeah
well won't listens much right so it's
it's kind of it's yeah it is the soft
targets in some in some sense but that
you mentioned the intellectual diet web
and I think that's there's two things
going on there's there's the nature of
the the views of the people within it
and there's the nature of the
conversation and I think that is why you
also talked about it is a really
enlivening experience and I had the same
experience watching some of the Dave
Rubin shows with my the Weinsteins and
Peterson Shapiro there's a sense of
intellectual adventure yes in these
conversations and I think on the Joe
Rogan show as well there's a sense of
that's what thinking looks like and I
think we've been starved of actually
seeing people thinking yes and I would
say another piece of it was that I I've
never really engaged to be perfectly
honest and listened with real integrity
and openness to conservative thinkers
people on the right I've been I was so
in the left bubble that it was like
legitimately my my belief was we on the
left are just right which is right about
everything so we just need to like wait
for the people on the right to wake up
and realize this there are they're
completely off yeah there's stupid or
evil or something can't really
understand why they are ever they are
and so engaging and watching some of
these conversations in the intellectual
dark web has really helped drive home
this perspective which was new to me
around
it's not that the Conservatives in the
right or our right are correct but it's
like we on the Left we need the
Conservatives for that dialectic we need
to think together to come to new truths
and if you cut out one side of it that's
that's inherently problematic and so you
get the idea of like we need diversity
of viewpoints if we're all about
inclusivity and diversity and inclusion
we need to be inclusive of different
political you know beliefs different
viewpoints and I think on the left that
can be it can be really dried you know
you don't have that which is the paradox
of the left the obsession with diversity
but diversity within a very
ideologically kind of narrow yes and so
you have some folks having really
interesting conversations that go into
taboo spaces were on the left you can't
go if you bring those up it's really you
become a lightning rod and there's folks
here who are you know and I think it was
Peterson or someone was speaking about
the intellectual dark web and they said
if we're gonna argue and disagree I want
to hear the best argument for that like
we don't want to set up straw man you
know and bad arguments you can dunk on
and you want to find people who are
really intelligent and articulate and
can give you the best argument for that
if you're pro-life what's the best
argument for your belief in that we're
like let's at least engage on on a
higher level of intellectual discourse
yeah and you know this issue of the
complexity of the world and of the
society that we live in right now has
come up and I have found in talking to
friends of mine who are into the
intellectual dark will have been also
have a background in complexity theory
of a friend of mine who I've been
arguing with over politics for a decade
now he's always pointing out to me that
you know universal health care for
example other societies have instituted
this decades ago and their systems are
not perfect but maybe better than what
we have in the United States but given
our unique cultural situation or unique
history it's not a simple matter to
transition from what we have now to
something else and we don't because of
the complexity of the issue we don't
know what could go wrong
in that transition you could end up
worse than we are right and so it's got
me thinking okay maybe we need to move
more slowly here I do think that
everyone should have health care as a
right that's my value proposition but
how do we get there I don't think the
insurance companies are gonna be much
help but it's like we need to make
allies here and and create a system that
won't lead to a collapse which wasn't
predicted because the value can guide
you to the end but the mean still
remains to be discovered I think it's
that back to that point the first stage
for me has to be getting learning how to
be nonreactive
yeah and it's interesting that we both
can teach meditation
know and practice like that is
effectively the practice it's being able
to yourself is the observer and the
content being observed having that
distance between I think without that
ability it's almost impossible to have
the conversation because we know from
strong evidence from neuroscience that
we make decisions emotionally first and
then post rationalize them second later
so with that in mind it's no surprise to
me that until now there's been just a
deep polarization and I think I see that
in the intellectual dark web I see a
level of non reactivity with mmm I kind
of just disagree with that they're
disagreeing with each other but kind of
having a generative conversation I think
that's where some of the power lies of
spreading that apps assigning like hey
let's have a conversation where we're
not just in a reactive loop mm-hmm and
it is about having a position as well
and coming back to your point about
politics something I heard Brett and
Eric talk about was we know that none of
the solutions work
we know that libertarianism doesn't work
for game theoretic reasons we know that
capitalism doesn't work for game
theoretic reasons we know that socialism
won't work for game theoretic reasons we
know all of these sort of solutions
don't work so let's we have a blank
slate we have all we have a yeah we have
we have to work with our evolutionary
toolkit because we know these this is
what we've been given and work within
that so that's a that's also a kind of a
really interesting place to start this
conversation from as well which I think
most of the people within the
intellectual dark web would say
certainly from a political perspective
we're starting from zero because we know
none of the solutions are going to get
us through right right
and yet we also have to start where we
are unless there's gonna be a complete
collapse and sometimes you need the
blank slate before you can build
something new I'm not sure if we should
be inviting that or at all it's too
excited about that you know that could
be this situation afternoon but you know
I really like to think about this in
terms of media technologies the
evolution of human consciousness is
simultaneously the evolution of media
technologies communication technology is
you know it used to be the drama around
the fire and just primal speech and song
and then the first script alphabetic
consciousness radio or sorry the
printing press we can't skip that
without the printing press there's no
democracy radio television the Internet
there are specific modes of
consciousness facilitated by each of
these technologies and the intellectual
dark web is very much the the birth of a
new media environment superseding the
old mass media technology is
decentralizing thought you know in a way
that mass media was able to sort of get
a handle on and you know the printing
press was what allowed for the French
Revolution the Protestant Reformation
information the American Revolution and
print consciousness literate
consciousness the type that will read
pamphlets newspapers is a very non
reactive form of consciousness in a
sense it's more intellectual and less
emotional it's not that there was an
emotion involved in politics before
radio and television but people were
able to consider the argument and sit
through a tower or lincoln-douglas
debate you know can you imagine people
sitting through a towers of politicians
debating with one another no way so with
with radio you had the risk of fascism
you know was being developed in the 30s
and there's one voice the Fuhrer who's
disseminating this image of the
fatherland you know all across Central
Europe and and then with television
which really came to the fore in the 60s
that's when images were coming back from
Vietnam and people were seeing what war
actually looks like for the first time
and that generated this tremendous
outpouring of compassion in the anti-war
movement right so but the the blue
churches Jordan green home calls it has
had control over television and
newspapers for decades now but that
media landscape that environment is is
dying off it's really only people over
35 that I think still look to the
Washington Post in the New York Times
and CNN and MSNBC young people are
online and they're getting their
information from these more unique it's
it's there's more diversity online in
terms of the conversations that are
being you're also starting to see the
way it's breaking down legacy media's
CNN MSNBC
it's too centralized so up that movement
to like blockchain and like digital
currencies is I think happening in the
same way it's decentralized with all the
beauty and excitement and also the
challenges and pitfalls but I think
you're starting to see you know this
post truth world where suddenly there
can be fake news on the left and New
York Times doing these hit pieces on
Peterson that is just promoting
blatantly false
you know insinuations and accusations
and so suddenly is like what is true
what's not and that dovetails into you
know when I toured in green halls and
Daniel smacking burgers pieces around
sense-making
and like what is sense making our our
capacity to make sense of the world and
then be able to be agents and have
agency and make decisions and choices
through having you know sense of meaning
and understanding but it's like data
overload so on the one hand it's
decentralizing we're also getting
completely swamped with data information
viewpoints how do we sort that what
sources do we look to like and I think
that's what some the intellectual dark
web is doing when I'm overwhelmed of
sense making its alternative sense to me
and it's been the cracks but that's
opening and the electricity that's there
that we both talked about people are
flocking to and it's showing people are
hungry and thirsty and and deprived of
some of this form of discourse thinking
and conversation and I think as a
journalist I've kind of looked at the
influx of fake news and the kind of the
continuing downward spiral of the news
media and been very concerned by it like
it's like I work the longer very
talented people I know that this kind of
anti journalism kind of conspiracy
theory is not it's at least only
partially true and I've sort of seen
since I've been outside the media that
there are ways of groupthink though
there's certainly a way of groupthink
and there's a certain kind of bias to
the media this is a blue church thing
that Jordan Greenhalgh talks about and
more aware of that since I've been out
of it but I'm also aware of the
difficulty of producing good news the
amount of money that it costs to send
someone to the Middle East for a long
time and understand what's going on and
all these things so I've been kind of
looking at how quickly it's losing its
credibility and been really worried by
that like it's it's like we're losing
the best some of that's irreplaceable
some of that's irreplaceable and then
it's only since the the breakthrough of
the intellectual diet web conversation
that I've got a sense that there is a
kind of bottom-up new sense making
apparatus that's being selected for by
the internet but these people are being
selected for by their by the number of
people watching them and Dave Rubin
talks about they're always being forced
together because they're being asked to
go on each other's podcasts there's a
there is hopefully a new sense making
and I also think this is probably an
early stage the intellectual dark web is
I've kind of called it a beachhead it's
like a kind of beachhead into enemy
territory to say okay we're gonna have
to start having a new kind of
conversation and I I also think that it
may well be in some sense the
intellectual dark web died
it was named by the New York Times
because it's no longer the dark web and
that framing of these are the voices
that are being kept out of the
mainstream conversation immediately
flips into no these are new media entre
you idiot medias entrepreneurs who are
creating alternative to the mainstream
media me Joe Rogan gets what ninety a
hundred million downloads and views a
month yeah allegedly he's the most
powerful podcaster so most powerful
media person who's ever lived
so the idea of that it was a fascinating
thing like at the moment of it being
named it ceased to be what it was so
that's one of the things and you said
this Matt like Joe Rogan seems to just
have whoever he wants Andres podcast
they could be timeout UFOs and aliens
psychedelics people like Peterson or Ben
Shapiro you know but there's something
refreshing about well here's a mansion
guy with a huge reach a huge audience
and it seems that whoever he's
interested in and he doesn't have to
agree with them on anything just to have
and that's something that's really
refreshing and this seems important yeah
and I think the other thing with Joe
Rogan is because you would never think
of Joe Rogan as an intellectual in the
same way that say Brett Weinstein or
Eric Weinstein is but he is part of the
intellectual dark word because of the
nature of the kind of conversations he's
able to host that he he's genuinely
interested he's genuinely learning and
he's genuinely inquiring and there's
that expand the conversation beyond just
academia or those who identifies
intellectuals and it and it Flags up how
and this is something Jordan green halls
talked about as well is that we have
because of the increased complexity of
the world and the chaotic nature of of
existing in it we've increasingly
replaced thinking with a facsimile of
thinking reactivity responses and what
this is again flagging up is oh this is
this is actually what thinking looks
like where you're able and that's a it's
a process of courage and it's a process
of self-reflection and all of these
things it's it's yeah mass media trans
people to say what sounds smart
in education major mainstream university
education generally trains people to say
what sounds smart
in other words it's not what's actually
thought through rigorously for oneself
it's what's gonna advance you in the
type of society that we live in and you
know one thing that's great about the
intellectual dark web is that I get the
sense that they're accountable to their
audience mainstream media is not
accountable to their audience they're
accountable to their advertisers because
that's who's paying the bills that's
right all right so that's a huge that's
a huge difference and that allows them
to be flexible nimble and they'll just
be like okay we've been asked to two of
us to do a podcast or let's have the
four of us sit down they're on a
different they're like guerrilla you
know warfare it's just a different a
different mode of interacting and it's
clearly effective and that was to Jordan
green halls idea of the blue church
versus the red the blue is still trying
to catch up the legacy news media and
the left which is kind of become their
hegemony like the mainstream no longer
the counter cultural force is trying to
understand how Trump and some of this
right you know some of the red church
has like a real warfare and we're still
lining up like in the Civil War and
we're trying to figure out the
technology or the moves that they're
making and until we can figure that out
they're gonna run circles around us and
I think we're just really in this
in-between space of trying to understand
what the landscape is I pick up as well
I don't think I mean in the UK at least
we don't really have much advertising in
news the BBC is is advertising free I
used to work for Channel four News which
barely has an advertising as well but
there is still the same same groupthink
and I think actually a much more a much
more powerful force is peer pressure
it's what other people will think of you
it's it's the groupthink within within
within any media industry I'm not so
sure the advertisers have much have much
power over that at least at the the
level of the individual decisions of the
reporters it's much more am I a good
person if I think this what will my
friends think of me what will other
people in the newsroom the reporters I
know I'm much more worried about what
other reporters think of them and other
people within the industry think of them
than the people outside it does depend
though I think you know with gamergate
that the way that sort of began was you
know popular gaming websites very much a
church siding with the publishers when
gamers were complaining about certain
things and that created it sits a little
microcosm of what's happening now in the
wider scale yeah it's we cannot trust us
sense makers therefore we need new sense
making apparatuses yeah that's right
yeah I mean it might be a little
different in the UK versus here because
advertising bombards you on you know
cable news networks especially maybe not
as much on broadcast television but you
know activists on the left have learned
that if you want to get someone like
sean hannity or anyone on fox news to
apologize for something go after their
advertising revenue and tell those
companies that you're not gonna buy
their products if they don't pull their
ads from that show and then all the
sudden the tune changes on the show so
that's yeah i mean that's that's an
interesting difference between the UK
and the US as well yeah this is a game
coming back to brett and erik weinstein
talking about it which i think is a
really great understanding certain types
of things do not survive encounter with
the profit motive and truth-seeking in
particular does not survive an encounter
with the profit motive
so universities news anything that
involves seeking truth is corrupted by
by by money in and so i think yeah it
probably is a very different situation
here and I think there's something
speaking for the the farsightedness of
the people who put the BBC together in
the 1920s was this is such a powerful
technology that we need to have it at
least an arm's length from government
and an arm's length from commercial
pressures which which I guess you don't
have we have National Public Radio NPR
but everyone on the right thinks that
it's controlled by the government
but it's also I mean the BBC is this
massive organization it's got huge
number TV stations huge number of radio
stations I mean no it's not like the
comparison is NPR's tiny yeah yeah you
get people really railing against
peterson with his patreon account and
people making a lot of money but a part
of me is like okay so you set up a
patreon account of people like what
you're doing you can be supported and
that's also just a different model
you know it's decentralized to a certain
extent
I'm sure there's problems with it it's a
viewership paying directly for the kind
of content that they'd like to see
yeah and and Peterson and these other
guys seem to be pretty responsive to
what their audience asks of them yeah
you know that's what's driving their
whole the media operation yeah
so it's not like these huge companies
creating content that they think will be
good for their advertisers or that their
bubble suggested is what people want to
hear and then they just beam it out at
everyone there's a new feedback
mechanism there's interaction here great
mmm I'm interested to ask you guys where
you think we are we we just got an email
from Ken Wilbur's people and they're
tracking the same sort of thing Ken will
be the integral philosopher our
suggestion my suggestion in one of the
the articles that I wrote was that what
is happening is an emerging integral
conversation so integral for people who
don't know is is the idea that there are
ideological ways of looking at the world
and integral is a kind of almost like an
evolutionary step change beyond that
into a space where we're able to see all
the ideologies but able to kind of
access a place beyond that and that to
me feels accurate as a kind of diagnosis
and I'm fascinated to what you guys make
of why it's emerging now what it shows
about the society we're in and where it
might be going as a as a conversation
well I do think I remember hearing and
it might have been Jeff Salzburg on
daily the walls were this city of the
intellectual dark web is integral
you know like on the one hand yes like
trying to I think a lot of people in the
integral community are trying to grapple
with say Jordan Peterson one minute he's
feeling completely integral the next
moment he's sounding not trying to
unpack it I know there's no clear you
cross the threshold in you are an
integral you're not you're always moving
back and forth whatnot I guess you could
stabilize or Center and more one stage
than another but I know one critique or
one challenge for Peterson and maybe the
intellectual dark web in general is that
when they start to critique
post-modernism either scientific
materialism or the worldcentric
post-modernism as if it's a mistake and
there should be more of a movement
backwards or away from that might not be
constituting integral thinking because
in in integral philosophy or theory you
want to transcend and include all the
stages and modalities of thinking and
all the truths prior so you want to move
into and above and beyond scientific
materialism which can be very
reductionist stick and materialistic you
know empirically back to science to
include more of the numinous than
mythological the spiritual metaphysical
but it's different than the mythic or
the magical their archaic levels and I
think sometimes I think of it as like
chakra systems
you know there's truth to each chakra
and a lot of people in the self-help or
on the left or in the there loves Paris
would love that yeah exactly
but there are these Hattie or that these
spiritual centers but there's like I see
Petersen sometimes is reclaiming like
amber orange amber red and these lower
chakras I get your room in order learn
how to really to money and to sex and to
power and those are difficult shadow
places especially folks in a spiritual
yeah community I suppose the question is
how big can your container be you know
how big is an individual how much can
you hold and that's that's part of the
that's where I see the link with the
intellectual dark web and the integral
whether or not it's an entirely integral
way of looking at the world I'm not sure
I think it's it's you know as you said
it goes up and down and it's just more
chaotic than that but you know I much
get that sense of that's what's needed
is the ability to
you said be able to hold the pre-modern
as well as the the kind of the higher
levels of you know understanding and you
know you mentioned the pre trans fallacy
before it's it's also being able to pick
out when is that pre-modern
understanding actually supporting a
bigger integration of society as a whole
because we do need all of those things
and I think it is confusing for people
because you know Peterson one you know
is there's many different Peterson's in
a way but part of integral is that you
can hold all of these different levels
of development and honor them and know
that they each have their own place
within the whole mm-hm
and so that's really you know that's an
exciting prospect to see society moving
towards there but it is like a birth
it's um hard yeah I mean I've studied
Wilber deeply from for probably five or
six years starting around a time I was
like 19 through Wilber I got interested
in this Swiss cultural historian and
cultural phenomenologist jean gebser who
inspired Wilbur in many ways and also
Sri Aurobindo who is connected to the
founding of CI is actually another
integral philosopher and I really like
Jeffers way of framing the evolution of
the human species he's a little
suspicious of the term evolution because
it implies progress and for gebser
the consciousness moves through these
structures in a way that's both both
progressive and regressive you gain
something and you lose something with
each movement until you get to the
integral which then it reclaims
everything alright so the archaic
structure is when we're still primal
people's immersed within nature no sense
of differentiation between the human
being has some special species with a
spirit that none of the rest of nature
has right then you get magical
consciousness it's the next structure
where human beings begin to grapple with
the power that comes from language and
symbol and you know they're they're
gaining a sense for Shan shamanic
practice
and ritual and then from there you move
to the mythic where story and narrative
becomes more pronounced so it's not just
like the power of single words it's the
power of the whole narratives and then
with the modern period right around the
time of you know me goes back to
Aristotle in the ancient Greeks and then
the Scientific Revolution that replaces
the mythic consciousness with this new
sense of the empowered intellect and
science and technology that can remake
the world too as we see fit for our own
human purposes and that mental structure
tends to cut itself off from its mythic
and magical and archaic roots it's all
the upper chakras and it denies and
represses everything below that as a
rational and needing to be at least
controlled if not eliminated like root
out like Sam Harris no patience for
magic no patience for myth we've just
got to live in the rational mind right
the integral structure which is not
we're not there yet but the intellectual
dark weapon I feel like it is at least a
space of possibility where that
conversation keeping the current post
modernity should probably be called
hyper modernity because when you look at
these post modern philosophers so-called
they didn't call themselves that but
they got labeled that Jacques Derrida
Michele Foucault shield Toulouse Felix
Guattari
they're using their deeply studied in
the history of Western philosophy so for
someone like Peterson to say that these
guys are undermining a Western project I
if they were around to talk to him about
philosophy we'd see very quickly to the
expert in Western philosophy some of his
critiques I feel like are missing the
target he's not critiquing Dario he's
critiquing college undergrad graduates
who haven't really read there right now
or maybe they've heard a few things from
their professor about him so like those
actual theorists are not the enemy there
are a lot of I think helpful tools
intellectual tools and ideas that we
need to incorporate into whatever the
integral is if you want to fight against
fascism Jill to lose
and Felix Guattari wrote some great
books that were trying to really
initiate people into a form of
consciousness that would be immune to
any sort of fascist authoritarian
takeover mmm and so when I hear Peterson
Braille against the postmodern theorists
I'm like dude you haven't read enough
this is also where we can all play with
the emerging integral or what's coming
next because you have people like
Peterson who is bringing some important
points and perspectives and then he's
missing the mark and mischaracterizing
Foucault yeah nobody's perfect but it's
great because then we can hear that and
say okay great let's take some of these
points that Peterson's point out to some
real shadows on the left and then post
murder knee you see where he's lining up
with people like Ken Wilber jean gebser
or whatnot and you can bring in people
who really know the philosophy within
post modernity or post post modernity or
hyper modernity and we can start to
synthesize and kind of piece together
what is that's not it that's not it
that's not it but what's the new and
Adam Roberts on our podcast did
something great which I guess it was
Foucault I don't remember about when the
new shows up it's monstrous
yeah it often shows up as monstrous but
you can feel an archetypal charge there
and Newman is charged that's electric
and that is just signaling whether you
love it or hate it or polarized by it
it's touching into a nerve center on the
collective unconscious level on an
archetypal level what's happening and
that's what I love young and Peterson's
idea of young bringing in psychology
we're trying to make sense of because
it's one thing when you're talking about
your own individual psychology and I
love James Hillman you know here's all
about we've had a hundred years of
psychotherapy and the world is getting
worse it's like what is going on and he
wants to bring psychology out of the
consulting room out of the one-on-one
it's about me my problem my pain this is
just my childhood my mom to this my dad
did this and bring it into the world I
would bring it into politics into
environmentalism but also I love the
project of Hillman because he's
reinventing he's saying if we take
psychology with just the care of soul
and the study of soul and we look at the
daemon as and the soul and the kind of
the spiritual core of us it all gets
flattened
and here is probably with Wilbur and
Peterson by flatland you know scientific
materialism which only keeps us
horizontal and the superficial level of
material reality on that point and to
your point as well of this cutting off
from the lower archaic levels with which
we need III often wander in my head with
with Peterson and Harris having these
debates I'm like is is it not the same
as psychology being stuck in the
consulting-room in a sense because in
order to integrate the the pre-modern
archaic what Terence Mckenna called the
archaic revival that's an experiential
mode of being not an intellectual one so
they can debate for a hundred years and
probably Harris won't shift into feeling
the numinous and kind of being down and
dirty in a cave dance to be like oh god
you know that's a tension that I think
is it's yet to be resolved because part
of it you know I think parents McKenna
was right part of that archaic revival
is reclaiming those ritual traditions
which for scientific materialist is
total woowoo you know and so it's a it's
a it's a difficult tension to resolve
but it's one I think needs to be
resolved in a different way than purely
through debate that's important but
there needs to be something else some
experiential element yeah yeah yeah I
guess this this is sort of pointing
forward as well
towards what a deeper resolution might
be because we've talked as well about
the intellectual potentially I see the
intellectual dark web potentially coming
to some kind of synthesis in terms of I
already think that some of them are
approaching that like Brett Weinstein
talks about how all maps must all true
maps must align so that you can get
there through evolutionary biology you
can understand kind of the world using
the evolutionary biology map you can get
there through Jungian psychology and
those two kind of they map onto each
other quite well you have the shadow you
have these biological drives that need
to be integrated you have and then
you've got potentially sort of other
other maps that also point in the same
direction and we probably argue that
Wilber
has has got one of those Maps as well
but that intellectual synthesis is only
part of the the issue and then you've
got the potential for as Ali was saying
you've got to integrate the archaic
you've got to integrate sort of the
bodily the the embodiment piece is is
such a key part because we're not going
to get there just with the Internet
mm-hm
and that's also a Rick tarnis talks a
lot about this right he'll map in his
classes
this large cycle where you start more in
an archaic magical you know
participation mystique and then you come
through in the new modernity in your
postman tree and on his graph it's like
we're entering just entering into the
underworld and it's a descent right it's
the dis the mythic descent into the
underworld it's the dissolution it's
we're feeling everything starting to
shake and and buckle and it's like
fractally all these lines of division
it's like what the center cannot hold
and a part of that might be again
playing loose with the words but like
that solar masculine driving maybe
mental is coming in and it's about
incorporating the shadow it's about the
sacred marriage with the feminine
bringing in the embodiment the
primordial experience as a culture
having lost all technologies of Rick
most technologies of ritual and
transformation and very few elders who
are initiated in these mystery
traditions that have held societies or
cultures together in many ways so we're
kind of entering into this you know
calabasas robert bly talks about cat
abysus it's like the descent you don't
know what that's gonna look like we can
all feel it whether we know how to speak
to it or not and I think we're just here
I'm enjoying being this conversation and
following the folks in the intellectual
dark web just trying to feel into what's
happening how can we best show up in
this moment how can we offer something
to be of service I think service to
other human beings is such an important
part of meaning making and feeling like
a life well-lived
don't want to just be sitting here
intellectualizing and thinking
I'm very much trying to find that
alignment between thinking out loud with
really intelligent people and then how
do we act how we lived those values in
the world important yeah yeah I do find
myself resonating quite a bit with
Peterson's message about the individual
as like the source of the sacred and the
the value that all societies must uphold
as the highest if they hope to avoid
various forms of oppression and it makes
me think that individual it's not
individualism as an ideology that he's
talking about because that in a secular
context is it it degrades into just
selfishness and get what I can for
myself and maybe my family would be the
one you know ethical sphere that I'd
include as part of myself but unless our
culture can rediscover the sacred then
the individual becomes just it it
devolves into another ideology mmm what
happens after death and what is this
life for if my individuality my ego will
dissolve at the death of this body how
do we channel that sacred value of the
individual into a collective project mmm
where what I do in this life in service
to individuality also in some way opens
out into a society where we're all
looking out for each other because you
know there's this retreat into a kind of
nationalism as resources become more
scarce and I don't think that's the way
forward it's not the way backward
doesn't put it plainly the only way out
is through if we're not gonna become
international and we can't do it the way
global capitalism tried where like we
discussed earlier it's like well you can
have your religion and your culture just
don't believe in it too much that you're
not able to shop at the grocery store
get a job and stuff we can't do it that
way we need to acknowledge this cultural
pluralism but in a way that there's some
deeper value Peterson I love this phrase
he refers
- it is a low-resolution grand narrative
mmm a grand narrative that's not so
specific that you lose the diversity and
you force everyone to conform to one
story but also not so diffuse that
there's no common value system then can
guide our activities as human beings
into the future because this is not a
very big planet and despite the idea
that capitalistic economists keep
preaching that we can keep growing
growing growing it's we're not gonna be
able to do that so what do we do what
are we here for what do we value most
what do we want to be doing you know
there's a want to speak to the paradox
of individual individualism or the
individual yeah because I think it's a
kind of cat the way I say it is a kind
of catch-22 like I'm I'm also very
energized by Peterson's focus on the
individual I've done a lot of sort of
personal growth work a lot of individual
development and some people would sort
of describe that sort of selfish or
solipsistic and my experience is that
only by really going deeply into myself
and really identifying kind of the
things that I have that keep me selfish
keep me divided from other people am I
really able to come into community with
other people
am I really able to make true contact
with others and feel that empathy and
feel that kind of that for me is that
the ultimate catch-22 and I think it's a
big sticking point for the left when
they hear people talking like Peterson
talking about individual the individual
because like no no it's about the
collective it's about the society my
sense is you cannot jump to that point
you can only get to that point from a
genuine felt sense once you've done the
individual work and individuation that
you then feel that you're then acting in
the society from a place of genuine
empathy genuine connection genuine
otherwise you're prop you're almost
certainly playing out your shadow and
playing
you'll you're crap in the world and this
is and it's yeah it's a really good
point something Alan Watts used to talk
about as well it's that and I think I
see this a lot on the left or you know
in progressive circles is that there's a
real effort thing to create something
that only really has an impact if it
doesn't effort it you know so that
coming within means that you're you you
know you're owning your stuff you are
connected to yourself and your
compassion and your inclusivity emerges
naturally because that's how you are you
can't help being like that when the ego
is trying to mimic that it's exactly
that it goes into well authoritarianism
at the worst and at least a lot of
bullying and kind of snide Ness on the
other end and so again that's that's
part of a necessity for me of this kind
of shadow work and also just
recontextualizing focusing on the
individual it's not a selfish thing it
is kind of a selfish thing but it will
lead you to a selfless place it's so
good so first I mean this is the
pendulum right we're talking about
different ways pendulum swings and I
think you're absolutely right that idea
that you know it's kind of like and it's
helman to saying we need to get out of
the consulting-room into the world but
there's been a move you know there's
like either it's all self work
everyone's in therapy for themselves
it's all about what's going on with me
no one's being active no one's going on
to the world trying to help change
systems of oppression you might have a
person of color sitting in a therapy
office and they're saying oh well your
anxiety or your depression is connected
to what your mother's did your father
did and you're not talking about the
system's level of oppression or violence
but then you also have this real strong
swing towards tackling the systems and
the systemic inequality and injustice
and collective you have activists who
are not only burning out getting
different forms of PTSD but are also not
doing the inner work around their own
personal trauma and healing work that
needs to happen and I'm always
interested in this in this intersection
of personal trauma and collective trauma
and when are you speaking about one form
but it's coming out another way and I
think there are a lot of people who are
fighting beautifully for important
of Justice inequality who might be
charged and really angry because they
have undigested unprocessed and healed
personal trauma however that could look
there's not to deny that collective
they're fighting on bit and on the
behalf of a group of a marginalized and
oppressed group but there's no language
or container to talk about like whoa now
it feels like you're talking about a
systemic issue but it's coming from a
very deep low place of PTSD and trauma
I saw a Twitter bio yesterday that was
kind of activists all angry like the the
fetishization of anger it's a real thing
that on the left it's like well you
should be angry look at the way the
world is it's like that doesn't seem a
very ground a place to make the changes
we need to we need to make right you
know this relationship between the
individual and the community or society
is it's a dialectical one it's it's
recursive it's a loop right because it's
not like we just come into the world as
responsible free thinking individuals a
certain kind of community is necessary
that values those things and instills
them and culture it's that and young
people so if human beings don't come
into a situation wherein there's equal
opportunity for quality housing you live
in a good neighborhood they go to a good
school they have good food if they don't
have get this equal opportunity they're
not gonna be able to become individuals
so you already it's it's it's a loop
right it's a chicken and the egg problem
if you don't have the kind of society
that values you know early childhood and
early education as the platform upon
which you then get free thinking
responsible individuals you're not gonna
get those as adults and so but at the
same time you're not gonna have that
kind of society unless you have free
thinking responsible adults to invest in
creating it and maintaining it so where
do we start it's like there's we have in
our work to do and there's political
yeah and it's kind of like clean your
room and maybe we should also
acknowledge it some people's rooms are
just two walls with no ceiling on it and
it's like they're trying to clean it
with hurricanes and rain that is
important to remember I think it's a yes
ad
certainly right but it's gotta start
somewhere my my own feeling is it's got
a there's got to be an acknowledgment
that of course begun have equal
opportunity right now but we have to
start somewhere because I've noticed
this and you know activist communities
as well trying to change an entire
system yeah where it is where do you
start start with the people in the
system it's not perfect but there seems
to be a kind of mismatch between
actually superior talks about this as
well it's like if you say something is
systemic then it's it's almost so big
there's like what the hell are you gonna
do you know so at least focusing even in
that model on individual institutions
like this institution is corrupt I'm
gonna focus with ten other people or
individual actions or individual actions
within those institutions you know it's
got to narrow down to a degree otherwise
it's completely unmanageable yeah I
started to get this feeling during the
Occupy protests in 2011 or so where all
these people are out there protesting I
felt energized by it but there was no
sense of directing that energy into
specific policy goals or initiatives
yeah and I got to realizing like we're
all railing against capitalism it's like
well it's so big it's such an
abstraction where's capitalism where's
capitalism and we're out there in front
of these huge bank buildings protesting
and I realized that you know I thought
any minute those executives at the top
floor we're gonna realize like okay push
the emergency button you cashed out of
the ATM is on the streets and will
disperse the people immediately yeah and
because capitalism it's inside of all of
us when we see money we're like we've
become money grubbers and so it's like
where's the enemy really if we're
fighting against something that's
systemic you know it's not separate from
you and it shifts the anger from being
just directed outward to a different
kind of emotion that's maybe like maybe
just as urgent but more curious like
okay this is something I need to
exercise from this self as much as from
anyone else sure and to Peterson's point
about that kind of medium resolution
grand narrative yeah the necessity of
EPs I was at Occupy London when all the
police came with the horses and we were
all standing there I had thought I was
like hmm I wanted to die for this and
then I was like you guys really sorry
for like what are we willing to die for
because that is the kind of energy that
actually does change systems yes when
it's like and unfortunate it often
happens when pea
in such a horrible position that it's
like well yeah that death could be
preferable to my life but finding that
you know the reintroduction of
meta-narrative in a new way for me is so
essential because it's like what can we
all get behind butts currently we still
don't really have that what can we all
agree on is worth living for and dying
for yeah that's also where Pearson's you
know one of his critiques and challenges
which is hard to hear from the left is
he brings back that old and charged word
of responsibility personal
responsibility and where is that in
these conversations and it's really
provocative to try and grapple with but
to the point about a low-resolution
grand narrative you know clearly are
fighting on behalf of the systemic
impressions and and certain oppressed
peoples but then it's like use this
phrase out in one pot or interview and
he was like he was talking I think about
the Christian Church she was like well a
certain boy you should have and say this
is my cross to bear and this radical
mystery that we're in as human beings is
we're all show up and we all have our
forms of suffering it can look a million
different ways and some there's some
archetypal the truths and level that
speech to like we each have a cross I
have my own cross I know it really well
I've been in therapy a long time I'm
working on my shadow but I don't know
you know what it's like to be a person
of color or there's so many different
ways but if we forget that truth there
is some mystery in which we're all here
on earth and we're trying to carry
what's ours act in the world and help
others and be a locus of sanity and
kindness and goodness in this world
maybe that's the trick yeah
individuality is the highest value but
your individuality is a gift it doesn't
belong to you in the sense that on the
one hand UK if you're religious God gave
you your individuality of your secular
society instilled any of those values
raised you to be capable of that mmm-hmm
once we start thinking that I belong to
myself I think we get into poverty and
without an overarching grand
low-resolution grand narrative about
that meaning me is the only me
yes me is the only thing left that's
what everything gets relativized and
culturally constructed there was a great
line in the Camille Paglia Jordan
Peterson talk where I think she said
something like the sixties that
consciousness is primary and a lot of
the time that the left makes the mistake
of thinking identity as primary is
actually the thing that goes beyond
identity that's primary that the the
revelation of the 60s and of young is
that consciousness the thing that
transcends our current situation is the
thing that's primary yeah that was a and
that was kind of the revolution of the
60s I guess sparked by psychedelics and
sparked by kind of the realization of
why our consciousness is so much bigger
than we ever realized and that's maybe
the sort of transcendent value that we
need to kind of recover yeah and it's
like a capital C consciousness that
doesn't exclude the body in a physical
world that somehow the body in the
physical world or manifestations or
expressions of this big you know capital
C consciousness right mm-hmm well I
don't think Camille Paglia was talking
about something that's stuck in the
skull you know well it was young or
someone I can't remember who talked
about individuation as the move from the
center of gravity being the ego or the s
the self with a small ass to the self or
the capital S that move of your center
of gravity your identity from small s s
self to large as self is a profound move
and that that like without that move
it's is that it's like you get what I
would say I'm out to a kind of socialist
value system but from the inside out
rather than being imposed by an
authoritarian government hmm hmm you
must do this way be this way you must
give this much in tax whatever it's more
intrinsically motivated yeah you know
and that's that's the shift that I think
I'm looking for do we you know we had
this thought the other day it's like the
word should there's a lot of shoots
especially on the left and it's like
should is a very interesting word and
it's a very interesting kind of state to
be in whereas actually
it what we're saying is we we can get to
a place where it's not a should like a
morality doesn't come from a place of
should it comes from a place of genuine
desire to do the things that we do and
the left has started as a kind of
resistance to the shoots of the of the
50s and 60s as a counterculture but it's
become its own yeah yeah I guess in the
Uni in terms it's or kind of Campbell
mythic journey terms it's like when
because we're kind of talking for those
risk of an ego self confusion you know
the ego becomes confused with the self
and it's this kind of deep narcissism
and it's more of a when the ego takes
its natural place contained within the
self then you should there's no should
you will you will behave in a certain
way and that that's kind of the back at
the point I was making of this this
desire for things to be a certain way
and should be that way and should maybe
be forced to be that way that's that's
some of where authoritarianism comes
from on both sides actually instead of
this when we reach a certain level of
understanding within ourselves and as a
community we will behave in a certain
way we will behave this way and it's a
you know it's a tricky one
it's a tricky one to get to but it's
very convincing the ego can be very
convincing mm-hmm I was not going to say
because I don't know it I just had heard
Brett Weinstein in conversation it might
have been under Rogen it might've been
with his brother Eric on the Rubin show
but when they talk about game theories
and they're talking about like these
valleys and Peaks and he talked about
it's a game B or I don't remember the
name less something talked about this
Archer who has become well-known or he
has seized youtubes that are and he's
apparently broken all the rules of
classical traditional archery I wish I
could members name where I'm kind of
butchering this but I watched I looked
him up and I watched it and it's like
Tour sensibility it looks sloppy it's
nothing it's nothing like the way we
will see archery today but of course the
argument is that this is how people in
indigenous cultures and and they could
shoot three at a time or shoot rapidly
and hit targets and be effective
in warfare we're not but anyway his
point in bringing that up was that in
this question of what's now what's
emerging what is how do we move forward
that he's saying it's almost like you
you're in the system you're in the
system until there's kind of a
spontaneous leap and step out of that
and you kind of step completely out no
one sees it coming it's it's a phase
shift it's like there's enough there's
enough that's evolved and you hit a
tipping point and it's a phase shift and
so I've just kind of been meditating and
ruminating on that like it might not be
what we're thinking we're thinking in
these ways and something might come
completely from left field and that's
what I like about the intellectual dark
web especially Brad Weinstein and Jamie
wheel and Eric and some of these others
is they're really remaining open let's
not let's make sure we don't think we
know everything there's an interesting
and I think it's probably the biggest
split within the intellectual dark web
because you've got people like Steven
Pinker in it who are like these kind of
very Pangloss Ian they're worried
everything's great the world is getting
better every worried about and even you
saw that on the recent podcast with
Shapiro wine Erik Weinstein and Jordan
Peterson and Dave Rubin Eric Weiss I was
the only one saying hang on I don't
think you're right I think I think
things are getting existential II more
dangerous even though you track kind of
wealth or whatever and everything's
getting better the risks are so much
worse and we're kind of screwed and most
of the the guys who I know I really
respect like the Daniel Shmack Tim
burgers Jordan green Hall Eric and Brett
Weinstein are all like waving red flags
and saying how on the existential risks
are so huge the technology is so much
better that we're in we're in a really
difficult situation but also we talked
to Daniel Shmack Tim burger and he used
that phrase the phase shift he said
we'll look at you can look at all of
these indicators and see wow this is
this is all getting very dangerous very
difficult they're hardwired tribalism is
likely to kill us and when all these
things are are true but if you looked at
he uses an example of a pregnant mother
the babe nine months it would look like
the baby was about to die because you
don't know there's a phase shift about
to happen and that's how he's choosing
to see it as these are the birth pangs
were something new and we don't know
thing we don't know that there could
very easily be a phase shift that were
that we're going through into a
completely new phase yeah yeah and I
feel like the best between you right now
is trying to cultivate a sensitivity a
heightened sensitivity to possibility so
that when that new thing that's gonna
get us through this bottleneck appears
we see it we feel it and it's not gonna
look like what we're used to
imagining as the solution and you know
as we've said the solutions of the past
that have been fought for once that
group fighting for it wins you end up
with a system worse than the one you
just destroyed right so it's not gonna
look like what we're used to looking for
them how do we cultivate that sense of
imagination that's required John Keats
called it negative capability you can
think about what's not yet actualized
and hold yourself in that space of
tension mm-hmm so that when that phase
shift is ready to happen you can jump to
the next chip that's gonna take us into
the future
I heard someone use the metaphor of like
a baby bird in the shell and the egg and
that there's some release of a gas or
some something that happens in the birds
suddenly after resting there says I need
to get out and it just doesn't even know
what it's doing it starts pecking and
it's fracturing this encasing shell and
then it just emerges into that next
stage it feels there's some resonance in
that kind of metaphor yeah so it's I
think in one sense we're things
are really bad right now and like just
to give Steven Pinker a little bit of a
nod like there's the potential for
something great like with the technology
that we have mm-hmm with a different
social organization like we don't have a
production problem we have a
distribution problem it's one way I've
heard it phrased in terms of there are
so so many hungry people isn't that we
have plenty of food
so we just need a new way a new way of
thinking with the technology that we
have
we could do something certain yeah
William Gibson who says the future is
here but it's not widely distributed
okay that's good
great thank you guys that's really great
as a blast thanks so much for having us
[Music]
you